"Perceptions of Childhood Obesity
and Diet Quality"
In response to the rising rates
of childhood obesity,
English children started
getting screened at school
and their parents informed
of their kid's weight status
and the risk
of excess body fat.
It did not go well.
Telling parents that
a lifetime of excess body fat
can increase cancer risk,
for example,
caused "controversy and anger."
Parents attributed weight
to genetics or puppy fat,
claiming their kids
had healthy diets.
One reason kids may not be
eating more healthfully
is that their parents
overestimate the quality
of their child's diet.
If it ain't broke,
don't fix it.
I mean, if they think their kids
are already eating well,
then there's
no reason to change.
The mothers of 2,000
preschoolers were interviewed.
What percentage of moms believed
that their child's diet
was good?
The vast majority.
What percentage of their kids'
diets were actually good,
even just according to the U.S.
Department of Agriculture's
Healthy Eating guidelines,
which aren't exactly strict?
Only 0.2 percent--
1 in every 500 kids!
The vast majority of mothers
overestimated the quality
of their child's diet.
Here's an updated study.
Another 2,000 households,
just seeing if kids meet
the fruit, vegetable,
and sugar recommendations from
the U.S. dietary guidelines
and the American
Heart Association.
Researchers looked at kids
from ages 3 through 18
and relied on reporting
from their own parents
as to what they were eating.
Overall, the majority of parents
strongly agreed
that their kids
ate healthfully.
So, how many of the 2,229
households met the guidelines
to eat even the minimum
recommended amounts
of fruits and veggies
and not eat more than
six spoonfuls of sugar a day?
Zero.
Not a single kid
in a single household.
On average, the kids were
eating more than 15 spoonfuls
of added sugar every day.
Parental denial
over the healthfulness
of their children's diet
mirrors the parental denial
that their overweight and obese
kids are even overweight at all.
Based on surveys
in more than 20 countries,
94 percent of parents
with obese children
believe that their children
are normal weight
or only "a little overweight."
94 percent!
And the greater
the obesity prevalence,
the more likely parents think
their kids look normal,
because they kind of do,
more and more.
But this underestimation
of their child's weight status
is a barrier to slowing
the childhood obesity epidemic.
And just as parents
of overweight kids
fail to recognize
that their kids are overweight,
overweight parents are also in
denial about their own weight.
This is not surprising.
Who wants to admit they are part
of a widely stigmatized group?
Of course, researchers
aren't helping matters
when they title their papers
about parental misperception
about overweight kids:
"Every cockroach is beautiful
to his mother's eyes."